<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An antidote against the errour in opinion of many in these daies concerning some of the highest and chiefe duties of religion as adoration, almes, fasting, and prayer.</title>
            <author>Monson, John, Sir, 1600-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24395</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08164039</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08164039</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40989</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51169)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40989)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1235:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An antidote against the errour in opinion of many in these daies concerning some of the highest and chiefe duties of religion as adoration, almes, fasting, and prayer.</title>
                  <author>Monson, John, Sir, 1600-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 121 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Griffin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life.</term>
               <term>Theology, Practical.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40989:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40989:1"/>
            <p>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST The errour in opinion of many in theſe daies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſome of the higheſt and chiefe Duties of Religion: AS <hi>Adoration, Almes, Faſting, and Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Theſſal. 5.21.</hi>
               </bibl> Prove all things, hold faſt that which is good.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Eſdras 4.38.</hi>
               </bibl> As for the tuth it endureth, and is alwaies ſtrong, it liveth and conquereth for ever.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Griffin.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40989:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40989:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable, and moſt worthy of all Honour,
<figure/>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Honoured Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſay nothing of your Vertues, nor my obligations, (which indeed the higheſt and beſt Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage would rather dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<pb facs="tcp:40989:3"/>from, then any waies expreſſe.) In obedience to your commands, that as a Law muſt ever regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late my actions, I here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you from the Preſſe with what you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſeen in looſe Papers; yet ſo as I have not preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to paſſe it under your name; becauſe denying it the ſubſcription of my owne, and too unworthy of ſuch a Dedication; though truly you could not blame me, had I offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in both, ſince I onely give the mettle, you the ſtamp that ſends it abroad
<pb facs="tcp:40989:3"/>for good and currant; ſo as you owe me pardon and vindication if it ſhall reflect upon either, ſince I reſigne both my own will and judgement to yours, and become rather paſſive then active in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing theſe indigeſted thoughts, being in all things reſolved to expreſſe my ſelfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in all affection to be diſpoſed of.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40989:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40989:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have obſerved a double errour amongſt the men of theſe times in the too long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining, or too forward anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of their thoughts. For ſome phlegmaticke and melancholy conſtitutions, like rich Mines, keeping their Oare within themſelves, ever carry their Candle in a darke
<pb facs="tcp:40989:5"/>Lanthorne to ſee their own way by, not to guide others; or are weaving a garment all their lives to weare onely to their graves. When others to the contrary, of more ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine and fiery natures, like the Iſraelliviſh women, are for war in their births, and ſo they may be delivered but of a little vain-glory, flattery, envy, ingagement of opinion, or the like, never conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how abortive and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhapen an iſſue they bring into the world, formed rather out of the foame of the brain then any ſolid matter. But I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to avoyd both extreames,
<pb facs="tcp:40989:5"/>and would neither be the Box of Oyntment that holds all within and poures out no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor the leaking veſſell that is ever emptying it ſelfe of what it receives, though never ſo offenſive and nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. For as I profeſſe againſt the thinking of any thing that comes from me worthy a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique owning, ſo I decline not the ſatisfaction of ſome neere friends, that have engaged me to expoſe this ſhort account of ſome of my private medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the ſeverity of others opinions. Though I am not unſenſible of the prejudicate prejudice they will meet with
<pb facs="tcp:40989:6"/>abroad; ſince I ſee truth ſelfe in many things of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nature inſulted upon, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cryed againſt, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> amongst the Iewes, not <hi>Bara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> but <hi>Jeſus;</hi> not errour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but innocence muſt be the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and ſuffer for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Yet under this contempt and annihilation (like our S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour upon the Croſſe) it is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greateſt triumph becauſe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conquered, when crucified, &amp; will riſe againe more gloriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for being now buried ſo lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in infamy and diſgrace. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if I can but contribute the Glow-wormes ſhine, or lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> twylight to its manifeſtation
<pb facs="tcp:40989:6"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n theſe benighted times of ignorance (wherein we are become blind by ſeeing too much of our new pretended Light, when the great Lumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries of our Church have either withdrawn their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, or been caſt out of their Orbe) I ſhall truly rejoyce, and willingly beare their cenſure that have not charity to pardon my failings; ſince in that affection I am the ſame to all, we ought to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to one another, and could wiſh my ſelfe a Sacrifice for their good, and the Churches proſperity.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40989:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40989:7"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Adoration.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough God as He is <hi>I am,</hi> a perfect and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle being of Himſelfe, all goodneſſe, the Spring and Fountaine out of which all other beings and perfections flow, might have enjoyed an eternall compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, felicity, and happineſſe, in Himſelfe; altogether unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Acceſſion or Diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yet for the fuller mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of Himſelfe in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40989:8"/>Attributes of his Power, Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Juſtice, and the like; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made the goodly frame of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whole Univerſe, and place man at the foot of the account as his laſt and greateſt work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Creation, to ſumme up an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> recapitulate the ſeverall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and perfections of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſt. Though he imprinte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon every one ſome viſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> footſteps of an inviſible Deity making every creature like ſo many ſeverall Character ſome greater, ſome leſſe, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their orderly being put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Letters in the Preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to ſpell his name <hi>Jehovah</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from a moſt legible hand; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Name not known to <hi>Abraham Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob, Exod.</hi> 6. as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> importeth the Eternity of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eſſence, who was <hi>yeſterday, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> day, and the ſame for ever;</hi> paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40989:8"/>preſent, and to come, with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſtence and perfection of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ings in him. So as with Saint <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rnard</hi> we may fay, God is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e being of all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>res; as they are of Him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Him, and from Him: not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at they are the ſame with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>irn, or that He is. A Name of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eer ſounds <hi>(litterae quieſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t)</hi> and of that immoderate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>verence amongſt the Jewes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s one obſerves) that it was ever named but once a yeere, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id that by the high Prieſt; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d being compounded of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Letters, (as ſome ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tive men collect) did myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſly expreſſe the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons in the one Godhead to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and Incarnation of His <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onne. The firſt, ſignifying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower for God the Father, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſecond Wiſdome for God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40989:9"/>the Sonne, the third Love f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> God the Holy Ghoſt; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fourth a repitition of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, to ſhew the reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of two natures in the Perſon of Chriſt: Altogether to declare Gods awfull an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtupendious Majeſty, his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection in ſupporting, Prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in guiding, Tenderneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and compaſſion in caring fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man, to whoſe nature he was united; and by it to challenge all the returnes of gratitude ſervice and honour, our ſouled and bodies are capable of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing, as the end of our crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. For God made all thing for the uſe and ſervice of man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> giving him the ſole Monarch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> over the creatures; and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for his own glory onely, re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to Himſelfe a ſing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> propriety in him. So that, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40989:9"/>would be the greateſt ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dge in the world to rob God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f any part, ſince He hath from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l eternity conſecrated the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hole man to his ſervice. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore it is not enough to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive Him <hi>inward feare</hi> without <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>utward reverence,</hi> nor a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all, but an univerſall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce, hand and heart, ſoule and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ody, with all the members <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd faculties of both, concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in all acts of his worſhip in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir ſeverall expreſſions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eale, piety, and devotion. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd not make it our Religion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be irroligious; nor with many in theſe times, account a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zy, proud, affected negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence, the beſt poſture to ſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od in. For ſurely though the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ody may act the Hypocrite, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a faire flower appeare upon a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ithered ſtalke) and perſonate
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40989:10"/>devotion without the ſoule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſoule can never praiſe Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as it ſhould, but the body wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beare its part in the Harmony and (ſo farre as place and other circumſtances allow it) wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make it all without as well a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all within,<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.3. praiſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord in the moſt awfull, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentiall, humble, and decen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poſture it can compoſe it ſelf to, ever ſhaping its behaviour by what opinion and the cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the place account moſt expreſſive of inward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and outward ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, even ſuch as in civill u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſervants uſe to pay their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Subjects their Kings, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> humble humility it ſelfe (th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more to ſpeake Gods glory) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it were poſſible in theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accented inarticulate yet lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> voyces. Though, as the ſoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:40989:10"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the touch of the ſtring, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nne by its operations, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tificer by the building he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes, the temper of the body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Pulſe; all theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd expreſſions ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed from, and declare inward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bits, our corporall actions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m our true mentall piety, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e eccho from the voyce that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes it. For the Adoration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the body is but the body of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>doration, the devotion of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ule the ſoule of devotion, that it animates and actuates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the reſt; even the whole man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the manifeſtation of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ory, knowing the moſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nly Anthemes and beſt Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ony ariſes from all parts in inſort together. Nay indeed is but a maymed and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed Sacrifice, (which is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ophane Gods Altar) if we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40989:11"/>leave any part behind, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> bring not the whole man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, our bodies as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſoules; ſince both with Sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> will but make up our re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſervice, in that <hi>we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bought with a price,</hi> (purchaſe His by emption and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) for that end,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> if the heart, the <hi>Primum mob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> be his, it will carry all the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> feriour ones with it, <hi>The ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to looke up unto the hils fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> whenee commeth our ſalvatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the hands elevated for an eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſacrifice,</hi> the knees bow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in an humble ſence of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> nothingneſſe, and Gods om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence, His Majeſty a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> our vileneſſe, with a caſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> down the whole man in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dreadfull reverence of his a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> full and glorious preſence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his Ordinances. This outwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40989:11"/>comportment ever ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low true inward piety, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>adow the body. Nor can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>igh elevated and Spirituall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bjects be known to us, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ade legible, but in their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; nay, there are no other perſpectives for dimme nature <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſee the glimering of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lory in them by the incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Himſelfe in his works, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or can he otherwiſe <hi>(quoad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>os)</hi> reveale himſelfe then <hi>ad extra.</hi> How then can we weak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en thinke to bring glory to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od from our works <hi>ad intra,</hi> ſpeake his praiſes in a liſping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alfe-worded Language, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a vocall and operative one? when the true counterpart and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt unerring copy of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oules affections is the bodies actions.</p>
               <p>Nor doe I in this contend
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40989:12"/>for corporall worſhip, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ceremony (a thing of decency and fitneſſe, or arbitrary only but as a morall duty, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the higheſt parts of God worſhip; if we conſider it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> its contrary, the grievouſneſs of the ſinne of Idolatry, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſevere puniſhments due t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, the manner of ſerving Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being the next Commanded ment to that of having a Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſerve, and a devotion mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> free from all ſelfe-reflections in its performance, in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> brings nothing to man bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhame (when he covers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with confuſion as a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to give the more glory to God) whereas in prayer and many other acts of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we doe not diveſt our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of ſelfe intereſt, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the good Husbandman
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40989:12"/>plough and ſow in hope of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich harveſt and bleſſed return. And it were a ſhame to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to be ignorant of this, when the very Heathen by the twilight of nature, that knew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot the true God, did ever worſhip their falſe ones in thoſe poſtures that in their uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd acceptation were moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive of reverence and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. And not farre to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them as well in the ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plances as realities of piety, by animating and ſpiritualizing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s it were, this bodily worke, (or rather worke of the body) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o make it become a ſpirituall Sacrifice to God, as well as Faſting, Almes, and the like, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. which yet are onely ſo conſidered in their ſpring and firſt iſſue, (the ſpirit wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by corporeall Organs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40989:13"/>and inſtruments, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ocean into which they runn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all terminating in Gods glory. For in holy duties <hi>Finis d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> formam,</hi> and addes truth t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Spirit, manifeſts and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> clares that we <hi>worſhip in ſpirit and truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 4.</note> 
                  <hi>John</hi> 4. the corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reall act taking its impreſſion from the Spirit, ſealing an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ratifying the dictates of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoule, turning the man out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and making that ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is inviſible. But to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more cleare we will define th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> duty thus:</p>
               <p>Adoration is an act of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion terminated in God, as the onely object in which ſoule and body ſhould concurre i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their ſeverall operations and waies of expreſſing of their awfull, pious, and reverentiall apprehenſion of his Eſſence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40989:13"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d Attributes, and humble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>proaches to ſo dreadfull a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>jeſty. Now this religious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſhip (which <hi>Scotus</hi> in lib 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t. 9. cals <hi>Piet as vel Dei cultus</hi>) <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dilectione, Sacrificii exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne, atque reverentia conſiſtit,</hi> ſaith he) and is a morall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rtue properly referred to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtice, as performing to God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ribute onely due to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eame firſt and chiefe Good, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>luding three acts in it.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Actum mentis, quo appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndimus Perſonae honoratae ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>llentiam.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Actum voluntatis, quo nos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i ut inferiores ſubmittimus, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> debitis officiis agnoſcere prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i ſumus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Actum corporis, quo ſignum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſtrae Demiſſionis oſtendimus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>oſtratione, inclinatione Capitis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>dgeniculatione, &amp; ſimilibus.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:40989:14"/>And therefore the School men ſay, As temperance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good, <hi>in ordine ad ſe ipſum</hi> Juſtice, <hi>in ordine ad proximum</hi> ſo Religion (which is <hi>Pietat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vinculum</hi>) <hi>in ordine ad Deum</hi> and is to ſhew it ſelfe in Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration as one of the high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> duties of piety, from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the infinitely ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed excellency God hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> himſelfe, as Authour bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of our Creation and Beatifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and this in the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> full way of manifeſtation th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> whole man is capable of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming. So <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> and <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Aquin. qu.</hi> 84. inferre. <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> duplici natura compoſiti ſumu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> intellectuali ſcilicet &amp; ſenſibi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Duplicem adorationem Deo off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rimus, Spiritualem quae conſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in interiori mentis Devotion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; corporalem; &amp; in omnib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40989:14"/>actibus id quod eſt exterius, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rtur ad id quod interius, ut per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gna humilitatis quae corporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> exhibemus, excitetur noſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>fectus in ſubjiciendum ſe Deo.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut as motion from life, <hi>ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irituali Devotione procedit, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eam ordinatur,</hi> The ſoule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt be the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Omega</hi> of it, which we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>metime illuſtrate by a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ude.</p>
               <p>For as prayer is firſt in the underſtanding, and then in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ords as its image, reflection, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d interpreter: So Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt be firſt in the inward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an (as the child quickned in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e wombe) and then it will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the throws and paine till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>be brought forth into action. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n humble ſoule (if truly and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owingly pious) never inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting but in a lowly body;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40989:15"/>for Adoration being firſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the underſtanding fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the apprehenſion of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the primative and chiefe goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and then in our wils ſubmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting our ſelves to him with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reverence and devotion, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> conveying ſome of that goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe to us; in giving us n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> onely a being, but the beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> beings here, with title to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eternall one hereafter, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhew it ſelfe in ſome ſtamp upon the Wax in the corp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reall acts of Incurvation, Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtration, and Genuflections, <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terpretativè.</hi> And good re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, ſince we cannot by ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(Attingere Deum)</hi> lay hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, we ſhould by ſenſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſignes ſtirre up our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeeke Him, and publiſh o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reverentiall feare in this Ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rent of humility towards ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40989:15"/>Maker, and teach others by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhorter and compulſory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay of example, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> give glory to God on high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>falling before his footſtoole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re below,</hi> Pſ. 95.2, 11, 27, 29.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 12.28. Micah 6.6. Yet we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt not conceive the acts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e body to be ſimply religious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves, but become ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nely <hi>(intentione agentis)</hi> by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tention of the doer, from all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich we will raiſe ſome ſhort concluſions bottoming them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon the ſureſt foundation, Gods holy Word.</p>
               <p>Firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that <hi>Adoration,</hi> or any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utward act of expreſſion, which by Divine inſtitution, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r its own ſignification ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be referred to God, is Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y if exhibited to any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in a religious way; Though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> civill worſhip or reverence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40989:16"/>of ſubjection is due to other in regard of ſome particular eminency and dominion giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to them from God; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they are a ſhadow, a dark picture, or dimme charact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drawn in little of that original greatneſſe which is in God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Him as in the fountaine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them as in the ſtreames, <hi>deriv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivè,</hi> weake and imperfect. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thus S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 22. <hi>cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Fauſtum, &amp; de verâ Religion cap.</hi> 55. ſaith we may honour the Angels in theſe reſpects <hi>Charitate,</hi> not <hi>Servitute,</hi> 1 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may worſhip the Martyrs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we would men in this life, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a reverence of love and Soci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or we may honour the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by imitation, not in our dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That Chriſt him
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40989:16"/>ſelfe (ſo jealous is God of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his honour) <hi>Inadorabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt ut creatura, ſi dividas ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us intelligentiis quod vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ab eo quod intelligitur,</hi> is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e adored if conſidered in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> humanity alone; yet <hi>ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>us verbum cum carne, id eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ens carnem ſibi unitam,</hi> is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>dored as conſiſting of two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ures, which by perſonall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>hypoſtaticall union make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one perſon, the humane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ure onely exiſting in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ine, who tooke the nature <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ly, not the perſon of man. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d upon this ground ſay the schoolmen, <hi>Non debet excludi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>nino adorationis Caro, licet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> non ſit ratio adorandi,</hi> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y be performed <hi>ſenſu com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>to non diviſo,</hi> in the <hi>concrete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> abſtracted</hi> ſence, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.14, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.9, 15.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40989:17"/>and was ſo practiſed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied on, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.2, 9, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 15, 25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.11, 72, 9, 11.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that Adoratio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the negation of it to any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture eſtabliſhes the duty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wards God,<note place="margin">Exod. 20. Deut. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>Deut.</hi> And that the Gloſſe obſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is expreſſed in two wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>bowing</hi> down and <hi>worſhippi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> that as <hi>Adorare conſiſtit in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> exteriori vel effectu, Colere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in affectu vel actu interiori,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> might contribute all our po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, both notions and moti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to the advancement of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſervice and glory. Nor is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> duty onely founded in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative precept upon wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Daniel</hi> the third is a large <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> raphraſe, but enjoyned u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt Commandement b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by <hi>Moſes</hi> interpretation, <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 4.6. and our Saviours C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40989:17"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. which is <hi>affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative</hi> to God, but <hi>excluſive</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all other creatures, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>its not the uſe of Images, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any other repreſentation, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>citative</hi> nor <hi>objective</hi> as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tive to, or termination of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> worſhip in the acts of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ough the Schoolmen by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t diſtinction have turned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> peoples devotions into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>latry and ſuperſtition) leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uction follow as a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon our diſobedience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d rebellion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18, 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 40.18.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that Adoration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s not onely commanded in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Law, and often repeated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Goſpel,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Matth. 4. Heb. 12.28 Rev. 15.4, 19, 10, 22, 9.</note> but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſied on under ſuch a phraſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> comprehends and ſignifies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> whole worſhip of God<note n="(b)" place="margin">Zeph. 2.11. Iſa. 45.23. Pſa. 2.3, 11 22, 27, 72, 11.</note>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that it did alwaies accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40989:18"/>Gods worſhip both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> publique, for the giving glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> to God, and good example<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> men<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Sam. 1.19. Nehe. 8.6. 2 Sam. 12.20. Ier. 7.2. 2 Chro. 20 18. 29.28, 30, 32, 12. Exod. 34.8 Deut. 26.10 Iohn 4. Pſalm 5.7.22.27.29, 1, 2, 45.11.86.9.66.4.95, 96, 97.7.132, 138</note>; and uſed as an abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſumme of all other duties and devotions by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Jewes; for when ſome preſſion and extraordinary occaſion would not allow them ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for more, they onely went<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Temple, worſhipped, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> departed, as ſome of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ancient Rabbins affirme. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> if they did not worſhip wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> out praying, they never I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſure prayed without worſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, but in that ſtrove <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>give him the glory due unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Name</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 29.1, 2. Deut. 6.10 Jerc. 26.2. Za h 14.16 17. Acts 8 27.24.10. 1 Cor. 6.20.</note>; and the Church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> due reverence<note n="(e)" place="margin">Lev. 19.30. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> : in rega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Gods more efficacious a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> glorious preſence there<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mat. 18.20. Pſal. 27.48.9.26.2.105.4.2 Chro. 7. Pro. 34. 1 Kings 8.</note>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40989:18"/>and the ſervice and attendance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the holy Angels to protect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d guard us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 34.7. <hi>Micah</hi> 6.6. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi> 5.1.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, that as Adoration was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>waies accounted a part of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ds publique worſhip, ſo it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s ever practiſed with moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>erty in the private devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of Gods ſervants; to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to themſelves the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ty, zeale, humility, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of their own ſoules, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the actions of the body to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rre up their devotions<note n="(g)" place="margin">Dan. 6.10 Luk. 22.41</note>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d to ſhew that being but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt and aſhes (which was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>hams</hi> Prologue to his prayer <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> 18.17.) they would yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th <hi>David</hi> become <hi>more vile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> God,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.20, 21.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, that Adoration is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ceremony we may collect
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40989:19"/>from thoſe expreſſions t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> very Saints and Angels in He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven uſe in their devotions<note n="(h)" place="margin">Rev. 7.11 12.22, 5, 14.</note> but a <hi>morall</hi> and <hi>perpetu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> duty, one of the eſſentials <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> true piety, and to continue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the meaſure of time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe, untill, at, and after th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day of judgement in the glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Saints, where no cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7. 4.10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 5, 14, 11, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, that Adorati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hath not onely precept for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> foundation, but for its ſuppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the practice of all holy m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> upon earth, <hi>Diviſim &amp; conju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim,</hi> ſingle, or as particul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> men multiplied into a congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation both in private a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> publique devotion<note n="(i)" place="margin">Acts 20.36, 21, 5. Mat. 28.9, 17, 15, 25. Exod. 34 8. 2 Sam. 12.20. 1 Kings 1.47, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2 Chro. 7.3. 20.18, 29.20. Eſth. 10.1. Neh. 8.6. Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 20. Exod. 33.10.</note>; N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40989:19"/>Chriſt however in other things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umbled, in this did humble himſelfe<note n="(k)" place="margin">Luke 24.41. Mat. 26.39</note>. And if God did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his for man, ſhall not weake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an put the greateſt debaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon himſelfe to exalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is great God? Nor doth <hi>Iohn</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 20. forbid it, but requires <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſpirit as the chiefe ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in it, <hi>verſe</hi> 23. and both as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n effect and high end of Gods Word preached, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.25. <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>But ſome may object that his was reproved in <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7.10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd a contrary practiſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, that <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſhua</hi> in his holy conſternation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd proſtration of himſelfe, was not checked for the act, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut the exceſſe in it perhaps, or other for not endeavouring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt to finde the ſinne, the cauſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40989:20"/>of puniſhment before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; the ſoare, before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> applyed the playſter. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for that where <hi>David</hi> is ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſit at prayer, wee muſt tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> notice that the ſame word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the originall (as ſome learn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> men obſerve) from <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 14.8. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.22. 20.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.32. compared wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18. that in all the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> places the ſame word is uſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the originall tongue, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not to be underſtood of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> geſture of ſitting, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in a poſture of praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> As <hi>David</hi> in the like caſe is ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to remaine before the Lord From all this reſult cleare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ariſes, that ſuch geſtures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt expreſſe a reverentia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, were commanded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God as a morall duty practiſe by his Saints, and are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:40989:20"/>imitated by us in our addreſſes and approaches to God, ſo farre as conveniency of place, age, or infirmities will permit. And if we cannot kneele nor fall down, which is a poſture in theſe times fit rather for the freedome of a private retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then our publique devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to avoyd ſpirituall pride which often grows and ſprings out of an affected humility, and the too forward cenſures of others, let us preferre Mercy before Sacrifice in this even to our ſelves, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.7. for God will allow it, if we offer all in our power, even ſtanding in prayer where we have no roome nor power to kneele<note n="(l)" place="margin">Neh. 9.2, 5. Luke 18.13</note> : And where we can doe neither, with old and weak <hi>Jacob,</hi> let us worſhip in ſuch corporall expreſſions as we
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40989:21"/>can arrive at<note n="(m)" place="margin">Gen. 47.31. Hab. 11.</note>; yet i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Miniſter kneeling even i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prayer is ſometimes diſpenſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when ſtanding in the Pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pit will make his voyce th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more audible and diffuſive o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods Word, and tends mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to edification<note n="(n)" place="margin">1 Cor. 14 17.</note>; for thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the obligation thereunto bind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſemper,</hi> it doth not <hi>ad ſemper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> alwaies in the habit, not i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the act, as in the comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of honouring our parents ſtill in diſpoſition, not i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expreſſion of it, though mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> chiefly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When we come into God houſe in regard of its <hi>relativ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſanctity</hi> called the <hi>beauty of hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> in that Gods face ſhine moſt there in his Ordinance and efficatious preſence<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſal. 5.7.96.9.99.132. 1 Sam. 1.18 2 Sam. 12.20. Iſa. 60.14.</note> though reflecting moſt honou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where he is honoured moſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40989:21"/>which made <hi>Salomon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand this reverence in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>when thou goeſt into the Houſe of God looke to thy feet;</hi> and the Prophet at the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Temple, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.2, 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When we prepare and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſpoſe our ſelves to Prayer, Adoration is the beſt in-let to our devotion. So <hi>David, Come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et us worſhip (or worſhip in our firſt approach) fall down, and kneele before the Lord our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">Pſal. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>, to witneſſe our humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, fall, and low eſtate in <hi>Adam</hi> by our nothingneſſe, the more to advance Gods glory.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When we ſum and ſeale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p our prayers with <hi>Amen</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">Neh. 8.6 Rev. 5.14.7.12. Heb. 11.21</note>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth as it is the Name of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.14. which we are to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire and reverence in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40989:22"/>ſence, not ſound; and as it is a ſhort repetition of what went before, and profeſſion of our concurrence with them, which made the Apoſtles wind up all their Epiſtles with it, in that it is <hi>Cingulum conſenſus, &amp; votum deſiderii noſtri.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. When God approaches to us in any extraordinary manifeſtations<note n="(r)" place="margin">Gen. 18.23. Iob 40.4.46.6. Luke 5.8. Gen. 28.</note> of mercy or juſtice<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Iob 1.20.</note>, our receiving of benefits<note n="(t)" place="margin">Exo. 34.8 2 Chro. 7.3 20.18. Pſ. 102.21 Rev. 11.16 17.</note>, returning of thanks<note n="(v)" place="margin">Gen. 24.25, 52. Gen. 47.31 Heb. 11.21</note>, or bringing any other Sacrifice to God<note n="(w)" place="margin">Heb. 13. Deut. 6.10.26.10. Micah. 6.6.</note>, <hi>votive,</hi> or <hi>devotive, Gen.</hi> 14.22. for God will not accept of meane, negligent, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functory duties<note n="(x)" place="margin">Mal. 1. Pſal. 99.132 138.</note>, nor ſuch ſervice and reverence as an earthly King will ſcorne and reject from his Subjects and vaſſals.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:40989:22"/>Now as the time is <hi>Alwaies,</hi> ſo the place muſt be every where<note n="(y)" place="margin">Joh. 4.20</note>; though amongſt the Jewes it was performed either <hi>in</hi> or <hi>towards</hi> Jeruſalem, for uniformity, Gods promiſe of his vertuall preſence being there<note n="(z)" place="margin">1 Kings 9.3.</note>, and <hi>Chriſts comming,</hi> whoſe types were there trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured up in the Arke; and not for any inherent holineſſe; yet Chriſtians may, if comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, worſhip (as they did) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Eaſt, for the order and regulation of their devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the commemoration of our great benefits by Chriſt, the expectation of his ſecond comming, the appearing of our Sunne againe in that Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, and the uſuall exhibition of Himſelfe, <hi>his body</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> in that part of the Church. But then it muſt not be done
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40989:23"/>to the ſcandall of our brethren, nor ſo repeated as if the Duty were riveted locally or fixt to any place, ſince Churches and the moſt holy parts in them, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.6. though eſtimation may make a difference, have no inherent, but <hi>relative</hi> and <hi>repreſentative holineſſe</hi> in them; nor had amongſt the Jewes, though their Three diviſions were ſanctified to three functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Holieſt to the divine preſence, in that all the Types were kept there, the holy of Holies for the Prieſts Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Leviticall Rites; the outward Court or Atrium for ſingle worſhip. Prayer and Doctrine. The two firſt were buried with the Temple, the laſt onely is common to all<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 56.7. Iohn 2.</note>, ſo as all ought to concurre in a reverentiall way of ſerving
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40989:23"/>God in places ſet apart for thoſe pious uſes.</p>
               <p>But to ſumme up all, let us conſider Adoration, 1. <hi>Quae Origo ſuae productionis.</hi> 2. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitio honoris.</hi> 3. <hi>Ratio exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the firſt is <hi>Actus fidei, nam fides oſtendit cur principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Adoratio ſit exhibenda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Actus Charitatis; nam charitas facit diligere Deum, ut optimum &amp; ſummum bonum, &amp; per hoc imperat &amp; facit adorare Deum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Act us Juſticiae,</hi> and ſo <hi>vel red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit aequale, vel poſſibile;</hi> it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes either what is due and equall, or what is poſſible. But becauſe we cannot performe the firſt, we owe the ſecond in all expreſſions of duty, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and devotion humane nature and a created being can attaine to. Thus <hi>Ranevius</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:40989:24"/>in <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Adora.</hi> As it is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one great end of Gods wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> preached<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.25.</note>, and pureſtact o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> outward piety, the beſt draw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Picture of inward reverence for the acts of the ſoule ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſecret and myſticall, and onel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intelligible in <hi>Veſtigiis,</hi> as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prints of the feet declare th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> way we walke in, the bene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſicence of the hand the bene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> volence of the heart, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> going as low as we can in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall geſtures, the depth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our humility and ſoules devo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and this not onely in re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of man, but God, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> judges and rewards us acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to our workes, <hi>though the ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cher of the hearts and reines</hi> not according to intuitiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowledge, but outward ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation and evidence. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as the beſt title to our ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40989:24"/>ariſes from our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reateſt abaſement of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lves, our glory heightning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om our ſhame. For like the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eacock when he moults his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pall Feathers to enrich his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lume, our diveſting our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lves of all outward great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe, and caſting our ſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owne at Gods footſtoole, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e way to be cloathed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onour, and raiſed to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hrone; like the beſt Timber, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich ever growes higheſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ard when moſt rooted and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cpeſt in the earth, we ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceive a meaſure of glory ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rding to our degrees of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mility, not onely in throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g our ſelves upon the earth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t earth upon earth, duſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on our ſelves, that lying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ried there in thought of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ortality we might riſe to an
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40989:25"/>immortall felicity for ever, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bleſſe the Lord with his bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Angels that excell in ſtreng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and doe his commandemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Pal. 103.20.</note> and all his holy Saints, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Worthy is the Lambe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> was ſlaine to receive riches, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> power, and wiſdome, and ſtreng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and honour, and glory, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> bleſſing for evermore.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> onely ſaying, but really ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> biting that worſhip in a viſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> adoration<note n="(d)" place="margin">Rev. 5.12, 14, 7.11.12.</note>. And if ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> humility and reverence ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be our glory when we glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> God by ſuch emiſſions in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, what poſtures low a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile enough can we finde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> compoſe our ſelves into wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we draw nigh into his preſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> here, unleſſe with <hi>David</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> introduce and uſher in ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> addreſſe to God and act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Devotion with Adoratio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:40989:25"/>for <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> gate is very low <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uilt, and hardly to be entered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n any other poſture; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oth kneele and fall down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. if we expect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is hand to raiſe us, his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to guide us through the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion, and diſmiſſe us with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leſſing, when we believe with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur hearts, confeſſe with our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>outhes, and wind up all with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he corporall atteſtations of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſoules extaſies and holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anſportation, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing leſſe then Heaven <hi>in Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gie,</hi> a dawning or in-let to an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ternall day of happineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:40989:26"/>
               <head>Of Almes, Faſting, and Prayer.</head>
               <p>MAn in his creation was made like unto God, that he might ſerve that God who created him <hi>in holineſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and righteouſneſſe all the dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of his life:</hi> But looſing that priviledge by his owne rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, was yet redeemed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> capacity of recovering by fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what he loſt by diſobedience<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and to the manifeſtation of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in all the holy effects of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, to which God laye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> claime by right of Dominion <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16, 17. And ſo we owe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40989:26"/>him ſubjection, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onqueſt, ſo homage, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. By covenant, ſo fidelity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.8. By communion, 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r. 15.10. <hi>John</hi> 14.17. So our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eareſt affections, which we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould the more ſtudy all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſſions of, for having ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſly provoked him by our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ranſgreſſions. And therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s all the fruits of ſinne have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rung from one root of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erneſſe, and hang or grow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon Three branches, our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oules, Bodies, and Eſtates; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o let us from one principle of Grace correct and alter their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ature, or new load thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ranches with contrary fruits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd productions. That the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>after of our Vineyard who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igs and plants, dreſſes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aters for that end,<note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 5.</note> may reap <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll and well laden Cluſters
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40989:27"/>from us for his care &amp; preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of us: our goods in work of Charity and Almes, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bodies in workes of Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, our ſoules in workes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Piety and Devotion, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with <hi>Aquinas</hi> 2.2 <hi>ae. Qu.</hi> 85. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 3. are our principall Chriſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Sacrifices, and acts of divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> worſhip, and therefore wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thy of our conſideration a par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> though ever to be joyned an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> united in our practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Almes.</head>
               <p>ALmes is a fruit of Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and called by ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Miſericordia,</hi> which is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> onely <hi>Miſeriacordis,</hi> a fellow feeling of others miſeries <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> regard of their afflictions, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a vertue dilating it ſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40989:27"/>of Charity, and like ſounds and ſmels communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive as farre as it can extend any thing of its influence. For the ſoule (as the wombe of the Virgin) not ſooner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives ſuch impreſſions from the Spirit of God, but they preſently quicken into deſires, and keep it in travell till ſome faire opportunity midwife them forth into charitable actions, in which it retaines ſome darke reſemblance of God in his operations, who from all eternity firſt framed the Modell, conceived the Idea in himſelfe of all things, then hatched and diſcloſed them in the ſhape of mercies<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to us in time which from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting he had decreed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the councell, not abſolute Soveraignty of his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40989:28"/>will,<note n="f" place="margin">Eph. 1.</note> in that his goodneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diffuſive, yet not leſſening by participation; for the Apoſtle cals him <hi>the father of mercies</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.3</note> to ſhew that as Father an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sonne are relatives, the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ever ſuppoſing the other; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> father of mercies in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, to declare their num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſſe, and that they an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the children as it were of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nature, no leſſe then Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Sonne of his Perſon; t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> teach us that this affection is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it were Gods darling &amp; a du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> grounded in the law of natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and expreſſed in that mutua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſelf-ſeeking reliefe in diſtreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that every man hath ingraft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in him, commanded by <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and the Prophets<note n="(h)" place="margin">Deut. 7.17. M cah. 6.</note>, raiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſpiritualized by Chriſt by giving us a pattern in a precep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to imitate beyond imitation,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40989:28"/>for <hi>be you mercifull</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s your heavenly Father is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull,</hi> in quality not equality. And by the Apoſtle it is called <hi>pare Religion and undefiled</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Jam. 1.27 Pſal 4.18.</note>. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sacrifice well pleaſing to God</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Heb. 13.16.</note>, nay accounted <hi>our Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouſneſſe</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">Pro. 20.2 Pſal. 24.5. &amp; 112.9.</note>, and a meanes of appeaſing his wrath<note n="(m)" place="margin">Dan. 4.27.</note>, being offered in<note n="(n)" place="margin">Heb. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Gal. 6.10. Iohn 3.17.</note> faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which made <hi>David</hi> ſay (as an Hebrew tradition tels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s) as often as he gave Almes, I will ſee thy face in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for the poore are ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and have a title to our Almes<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pro. 3.27.</note>. So as here juſtice and mercy doe meet and kiſſe each other, yet become not a Righteouſneſſe juſtifying but declaratory, and an evidence of our juſtification hereafter, in that we endeavour to do ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice here, <hi>Snum euique tribuere,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:40989:29"/>which made the Jewes ſay i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> begging give me the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and doe not by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Mammon of the poore turne it to the unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mammon, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.11. for then it will prove a ſinne f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> damnable in the negation of it, though neither meritorious nor ſatisfactory for ſinne in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> higheſt perfection, as a <hi>Goe y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> curſed into everlaſting flame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> belongs to it;</hi> and therefore we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it good to finde out ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or direction to regulata our ſelves by, in the diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>charities,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſince Chriſt ſeems to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a giving without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as the beſt meaſure t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> give by; when he ſaith, <hi>Sell a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that thou haſt and give it to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> poore</hi>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat. 19.21.</note>. But to this I anſwer as will plainly appeare from
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40989:29"/>the context, that it was but a command of triall, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to the boaſting young man, and no precept challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging univerſall obedience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not reconcilable to many other places of Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. And therefore out of generall principles and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples not perſonall Mandates we muſt forme our care and compaſſe to ſteere by in this ſo weighty duty. And our firſt rule ſhall be, to be as univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall in our obedience, as God is in his command, <hi>Doe good to all, though chiefly to the houſhold of faith</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">Gal. 6.10</note>; rather ſeeking fit objects for our charity, then ſuffering them to finde us, in that we are but the poore thens Stewards who have an intereſt both in our wealth and increaſe, ſo as their propriety
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40989:30"/>lieth in our poſſeſſions, which we ought at leaſt weekly to account for, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2. and to make our ability the gage and ſize of our bounty, juſtice, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> charity to them, with relation to our families, condition, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and other circumſtances. But ſome from a computation of the Jewes laying aſide a Tenth part of all their Incomes every <hi>Third yeere</hi>
                  <note n="(r)" place="margin">Deut. 26.12. &amp; 14.28.</note> for chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table uſes, would in a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that oblige us to an aſſignation of a <hi>Fifteenth part</hi> every yeere, beſides the mercy and compaſſion we are to uſe in caſe of <hi>debt</hi> or other engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Deut. 13.1, 2.</note>, as the higheſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of righteouſneſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent though imperfect, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.27. And ſurely except we goe beyond them in this, we fal much ſhort
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40989:30"/>of our duty, ſince the Goſpell is but a Lecture or Epiſtle of love, and love the completion of our Evangelicall Law. Yet I am not ſo ſevere as to tie any body to this rule; for then though love may be in the act, it were not an act of love, which for the meaſure of its expreſſions ought to be vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, free and elective; which truely and indeed is the ground of our reward. Thus the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6. <hi>He that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>eth bountifully ſhall reape bountifully.</hi> And who would be ſparing of his ſeed that were ſure of an anſwerable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe? Yet here we muſt ſet and tune our charities to the limitations our callings and relations put upon us, like Muſicke, neither too high nor too low, the Meane being the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40989:31"/>part that alwaies ſounds beſt in Gods eares, and that he rewards moſt, though Gods glory not our own advantage ſhould be the object and end of it; for that is <hi>not given,</hi> but <hi>put to intereſt,</hi> that would not be given did he not expect a retribution of advantage And therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to <hi>caſt our Bread upon the waters</hi> 
                  <note n="(t)" place="margin">Eccleſ. 11 1.</note>; to ſow our ſeed in the moſt barren ſoyle, the poore mans breaſt, where it may ſeem to be loſt; and this too without any taint or mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of vaine-glory<note n="(v)" place="margin">Matth. 6.1.</note>; not giving to be ſeen, though we may be ſeen in giving; for though we muſt not paint vice into a vertue, vertue may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in its own beauty open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unmasked; <hi>Our lights muſt ſhine,</hi> though the end of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40989:31"/>holding them forth muſt be Gods glory, not their own in appearing. And if we thus ſerve God, God will bleſſe us, in our<note n="(w)" place="margin">Pſal. 41.1, 2, 3.</note> perſons, in our <note n="(x)" place="margin">Prov. 11.24, 25.</note> purſes, in our<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſa. 37.25 26. Prov. 13.22. 2 Cor. 99. Pſal. 112.2, 3.</note> poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for it is not onely given to the poore, but Chriſt in them<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat 25.43.</note>; and ſo ſure not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be recorded in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<note n="(b)" place="margin">Acts 10.4, 31.</note>, but rewarded both temporally and eternally<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus 4.12 17, 22, 29. Prov. 11.17, 16, 6, 25, 21, 22, 28, 27. Job 29.31. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 12 20.</note>. For the Chriſtians Almes is his purſe<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eccl. 29. 1 Tim. 5 8. Gal. 6.10.</note>, which fils by emp tying; ſo as there is a gainfull expence, a thriving prodiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity as well as a prodigall thrift<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pro. 1.3, 7 &amp; 11.24.</note>; an improving our Talent, by uſing, not burying it; by communicating both our ſelves and ours in workes of <hi>mercy</hi> to others, whether by the lips or hands, inſtruction, or reliefe<note n="(f)" place="margin">Lev. 19 17 Pſal. 51. Iſa. 58. Prov. 1.4.33, 4, 2, 8.</note>. For he that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40989:32"/>thus gives to the poore lend to the Lord <note n="(g)" place="margin">Prov. 19.17.</note>; and if God be our debtor (O moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſcent, in that he that gives all to us is content to borrow from us!) He will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay with intereſt<note n="(h)" place="margin">Mat. 10. Luke 6. Pro. 14.21, 23.</note>; and if we become <hi>eyes to the blind and feet to the lame;</hi> He will never ſuffer us to want light to direct, and limbs to carry us to him for mercy in our neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Job</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>From all which conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſince we are but God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Almoners, and the poore man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Almes box, let us give with a large heart and an open hand, knowing that we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Gods bleſſings like the ground that drinketh in the raine, but to make it more fruitfull; and the ſtomacke that takes not in the meat (its
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40989:32"/>food) to monopolize, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ribute it to the moſt mean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd remote members, not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ury nor conſume, but to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge and improve them for Gods glory.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as the chiefe end for which we were created, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in a thankfulneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or our redemption, <hi>Lu.</hi> 1.74, 75</p>
               <p>Thirdly, for the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in regard of the bond of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ature, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, as part of our evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for Heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rov.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 8.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7. and ſure markes of our election, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. Our goods being nothing to us, till boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y animate and ſend them abroad with ſincerity, not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to do good to others; but then they will prove like the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40989:33"/>Widdows myte more ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and of richer value <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ballance of the Sanctuary then the Indies would be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Mine, the Oare in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Earth, where it lies uſeleſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> us. So as the Chriſtian ſhould be like the Clouds, emptying themſelves for others uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and dropping refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if not fatneſſe on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> below them, even by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of God himſelfe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring Mercy before all other Sacrifices, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.13.12.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 6. which is the cauſe it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſometimes called perfection <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.48.19.21. If juſtice be joyned to it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. For we muſt not feed the poore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome wilde beaſts doe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> young ones, upon plunder and rapine; not with others bread, but our owne; even ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40989:33"/>taken from our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary not ſuperfluous diet, to relieve them that want. <hi>For with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed, Heb.</hi> 13.16, not ſo much in reſpect of our goods, as our goodneſſe, which he values according to the affection they proceed from originally, our love to him ever including that to our brother. So as there is but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus amor, duplex objectum;</hi> and therefore when <hi>affectio cordis</hi> goes with <hi>Opus manuum; a contrario,</hi> a ſtony heart without commiſeration and beneficence, and a withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or contracted hand, that puts not forth it ſelfe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, God hates. For he is the weigher of the ſpirits as well as the purſe, and accepts the gift when offered as a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of gratitude, not as a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40989:34"/>bribe to corrupt the Judge, that by doing ſome good we might be licenced to Act the more evill, never valuing our purſes, unleſſe our perſons are firſt his, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. and that we give our ſoules as well as our ſubſtance, which we ſhall need no other encouragements for then to conſider</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the object of our Charity is not the poore man, but Chriſt in him; <hi>For I was naked, and ye cloathed me not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hungry, and you fed me not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the matter of our Charity is not ours but Gods; an eare onely out of the full harveſt. He hath given us ſome crumbs from a well furniſhed board, ſome drops from a cup that runnes waſte.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the end of our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40989:34"/>for <hi>Da &amp; debitor ero,</hi> if we give pence, God will repay us pounds; for Graines maſſy <hi>weights,</hi> and thoſe <hi>of glory;</hi> for drops of cold water, rivers of joy and pleaſure for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. So that at our generall accounts, though the ſumme and totall of our di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>burſments are little or rather Cyphers. nothing to what we owe: in our receipts God will adde figures to them, not onely to exceed our numeration but to poſe Arithmetick it ſelfe, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying our joyes beyond Multiplication, and ſumming them up in an eternall felicity, a happineſſe beyond augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or diminution. So as if we lay our foundation in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, we ſhall raiſe a ſtructure of glory, and gaine an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that is never to be loſt,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40989:35"/>become <hi>heires of God,</hi> nay <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heires with Chriſt</hi> for ever and ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Faſting.</head>
               <p>FAſting, as it is a forbearance of Meat, is of an indifferent nature, neither good nor bad, but in order to the ends for which it is performed. And if uſed as a holy Diſcipline, which every Chriſtian is to exerciſe upon himſelfe, may be accounted a kind of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Sacrifice as an act of ſelfe deniall, and more particular conſecration of our ſelves to God, both bodies and ſoules to a higher eminency of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſervice, by an abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40989:35"/>of our ſelves the more from all ſenſuall and worldly thoughts and delights, as farre as neceſſity or decency will permit; that by the hunger of the body the ſoule may be put into a divine emulation after Spirituall food, and make a heavenly man become as it were an earthly Angell; if he performe it with preparation, ſeparation, confeſſion, and contrition, annoynting his head (that is Chriſt in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) in works of charity, and waſhing his face (his ſoule) in repentant teares, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. But this may be either <hi>private</hi> or <hi>publique.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A private Faſt was a votive one in the old Law<note n="(a)" place="margin">Num. 30 2.</note>, and a duty commanded in the new Teſtament. In that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our doth not onely approve
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40989:36"/>the Phariſees faſting twice a weeke (if purged and refined from the alay of hypocriſie and vain-glory) but adde to it, and the practice of St. <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciples, a precept<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 19.14, 15. Mat. 2.19, 20.</note>, that after the Bridegroomes taking away they ſhould faſt; with rules both for the manner of it<note n="(c)" place="margin">Matth 6. Luke 5.33 35. Jam. 4.9.</note>, and Muſicall part, the well tuning of it, which he left to their owne elections. And therefore let us be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as at all times to live ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly and temperately<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.19. Gal. 5.21. Rom. 13.13. Titus 2. 1 Theſ. 5. 1 Pet. 4.3.</note>, in regard of their neceſſity and happy uſe to be frequent in our holy Faſting, which if rightly performed (as the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the thred) will ever uſher in a bleſſing and reward<note n="(e)" place="margin">Matth. 6.</note>, yet it is not the act but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention that commends it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as it is a fruit of <hi>godly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40989:36"/>ſorrow,</hi> and <hi>corrective juſtice,</hi> when from a reflection of our ſinnes paſt we thus puniſh them, <hi>Judge our ſelves to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent being judged</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Cor. 11 31.</note>, which ever includes execution as well as ſentence in it<note n="(g)" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.11. Jam 4.9. Joel 2. Luke 23.20, 29. Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 10.3. Pſal. 35.</note>. In that the crucifixion of ſinne is the life of vertue, and made one ſay <hi>Semper virtuis cibus jeju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uium fuit.</hi> Faſting or taking meat from the Body is the food of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as it diſpoſes to other holy duties, wings our prayers and makes them more prevalent. True it was uſed for the obtaining the holy Ghoſt<note n="(h)" place="margin">Acts 2.</note>, in the ordination of Miniſters, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.33, 37. wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of miracles<note n="(i)" place="margin">Matth. 17 21.</note>; and as it was the firſt Commandement<note n="(k)" place="margin">Gen. 3.3.</note>, the life of Heaven, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Promulgation of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40989:37"/>the Law<note n="(l)" place="margin">Exod. 24.18.</note>, and Prologue to the Goſpel<note n="(m)" place="margin">Mat. 4.</note>.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, as a part of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worſhip: Thus <hi>Anna</hi> ſerved the Lord with <hi>Faſtings and Prayer</hi>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">Luke 2.37, 38.</note>; the one the ſoules the other the bodies Sacrifice<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſal. 35.</note> though when twins they are of moſt prevalency with God as in <hi>Cornelius</hi>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">Acts 10.4</note>. For food (which is the teat of ſinne) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken away, will humble and ſtarve it; and the killing of that will make us live more vigorouſly to God, and gaine us the better audience in his great Court of Requeſts, our ſervice to him being a ſure title of his favour to us.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, as it is medicinall, for the preventing of ſinne, and correcting of our too ranke and mellow ſoile, which of it ſelfe is too apt to bring
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40989:37"/>forth ſuch weeds and luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous growth<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.27.</note>; for the body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> nouriſhed with ſweet, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ule with ſoure or no meats; which makes our God like a good Falconer give us tyring, and keepe us ſharpe, that we might ſoare and fly the higher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our meditations and gain an evidence of the Spirituality of of our condition.</p>
               <p>As a means to advance our charitie, enabling us to give the more to the <hi>poore,</hi> when we are ſparing towards our ſelves<note n="(r)" place="margin">Iſa. 58.7.</note>; for without that our forbearing of meat will be but the figure of famine, not image of a Religious faſt, or the divels Faſt onely, in not eating, if not by Almes feeding the empty<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Acts 10.4 31. Dan. 4.27. Jonah 3.7, 8.</note>. Or that of the <hi>beaſts</hi> in <hi>Nineveh,</hi> which ended onely in hunger.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:40989:38"/>6. As a part of that <hi>Righte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ouſneſſe</hi> wherein we are <hi>to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Scribes and Phariſees,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we will entitle our ſelves to the reward of it in Heaven<note n="(t)" place="margin">Luk 18.12</note>. For it is an integrall part of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> devotion, and reckoned with Prayers and Almes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Though their ſevere practice of it doth ſhame our loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> profeſſion. Their falſe and hypocriticall Faſts, (faſting though not as they ſhould) o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not faſting at all.</p>
               <p>Seventhly and laſtly, as a part of the diſcipline of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>to afflict the ſoule</hi>
                  <note n="(v)" place="margin">Iſa. 58.3, 5. Joel 12.13. Levit. 23.29, 32.</note>, wherein every ſenſe to the proportion of the pleaſure it tooke in ſinne, ſhould ſhare i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuffering. Which made ſome of the learned obſerve, that the ſame word in the originall ſignifies both an eye and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40989:38"/>that as it is the chiefe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>et of ſinne into the ſoule, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight upon the firſt ſight of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> againe weepe its own pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce, and ſhed teares to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence the hearts remorſe. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I am ſure that if that be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>fe mourner, (as it ought) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſenſuall appetite, and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inferiour ſervants will put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Blacks, and beare their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall parts in its ſufferings. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y ſuch was the humble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce many penitents in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er times had of their ſinnes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> (<hi>Hornil.</hi> 3. <hi>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Antioch</hi>) obſerves; fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing no confidence in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elves, nor waies to extenuate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r iniquities, they durſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for ſhame and abhorrence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their vildeneſſe, preſume <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeake their wants, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ate Gods pardon in their
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40989:39"/>owne names; but betoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves to the Beaſts (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Joel</hi> 1.<note place="margin">* Rom. 8.</note> and <hi>Jona</hi> 3.) to gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> out their wofull complaints by making them partners their ſufferings; and cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> little infants to faſt, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> innocent cries might be hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for their loud ſinnes; nay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a reverent Divine ſaith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pentance may be pardoned greater abſurdity then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for ſo unſpeakable are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> griefs and compunctions with in (if true) as ſhee ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> times to common judgement is guilty of actions more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable; not willing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any ſhould eſcape a ſhare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> her ſorrows, but wiſheth the whole frame of nature un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinged in aſympathy with her the Sunne to withdraw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> light, the Earth to keepe back
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40989:39"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpring, the infant to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reaſt, nor the beaſt a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e; by theſe effects to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the more ſenſible of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſgreſſions, and the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ying our ſelves all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d comforts; making the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pavement our richeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ins, anguiſh and ſorrow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bread; our drinke ſalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>res; till Gods pardoning your and refreſhing beames <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me to relieve us in ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es of preſſure or particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ertions.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom all, this concluſion is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be raiſed, that as the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ry object of our faſtings and humiliations, is ſinne, and Gods diſpleaſure for it: Our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e and ends ought to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s glory and our owne <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ndment.</hi> Though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they may be kept for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40989:40"/>the averſion of publique <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> private judgements, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an outward evidence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> inward humiliation und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them<note n="(w)" place="margin">2 Sam. 11.11. 1 Kings 8. 2 Chro. 6.24, 25. Exod. 17. Lam. 3. Iſa. 22. Jere. 22. Jer. 9.1. Dan. 9.10, 3. Pſa. 33.109 23, 78, 106 31, 50, 81. 2 King. 19.20, 22.</note>, beſides thoſe oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> great ends before expreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Onely let us exclude all hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall ſinfull and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ones from all relation to the ſoules happineſſe.</p>
               <p>For it is not the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers faſt, to keepe pure the ſenſes; nor the Polititians faſt to encreaſe our plenty, and harden our ſelves for want and ſufferings; nor the Miſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faſt, that keepes empty h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> belly to feed his purſe; not <hi>Ahabs,</hi> to murther and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the innocent; nor the poore mans faſt, <hi>jejunium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> junii,</hi> as one cals it, that faſt becauſe he hath not to eate nor the <hi>Gluttons,</hi> that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beares
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40989:40"/>one meale that he might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ble ballance his veſſell at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>other, not as an abſtinence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h Meate, but as ſawce to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pen his appetite in eating; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> to digeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rfet, nor to humble the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dy, unleſſe it be in order to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſanctifying of the ſoule; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t it is onely the ſtampe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lineſſe and ſanctified ends, that makes a faſt currant, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oes it valve with God; yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this we muſt obſerve a <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and moderation,</hi> not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering a friend when wee would deſtroy an enemy.</p>
               <p>Now as <hi>Private</hi> ſo <hi>Publique <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aſts</hi> are in their rules and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tations almoſt interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, being both of the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are and onely differing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> election of the Time, Place and Company; for in private
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40989:41"/>Faſts, the muſicall part, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> well tuning of them is ours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> every particular mans as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> condition and ſpirituall eſtate requîres it: but <hi>publique</hi> Faſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are ever to proceede from the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſupreame civill Magiſtrate p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily, though derivatively and by the Church; for no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtriving for a maſtery is crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unleſſe he ſtrive lawfully, ſaith the Apoſtle. And the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they command and exact ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obedience<note n="(x)" place="margin">Num. 10. Deut. 33.3. Iſa. 1.58. Joel 2.15. Zac. 7.5. Ion. 3.7. 1 Pet. 2. 1 Sam. 7. 1 Kin. 2.21. Eſth. 3.</note> if called fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the obtaining ſome publique<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mercy, or averting ſome judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for where <hi>Singula g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerum,</hi> as well as <hi>Genera ſing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> lorum,</hi> all are concerned, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> becomes every particular man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intereſt multiplied; for like<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many ſticks in a faggot cloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bound, commonly they burn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or are preſerved together. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:40989:41"/>therefore in our greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities when all humane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>helpe fayles us, let us after the example of the beſt men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd times have our eyes in this way fixt upon God,<note n="(y)" place="margin">2 Chor. 20. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 21. '3. Neh: 1.9. Eſt. 4. Je. 36 Zeph. 1.2. Iſa. 55.6.58. Joel. 1.2. Am 4.12. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n. 10.</note> being many and yet but one man in publique duties, when one in dangers, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.32.</p>
               <p>But in publique Faſts ſome are fixt, and ſtanding both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law and Goſpel<note n="(z)" place="margin">Lev. 23.27.32. Zach. 8.19 M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r 9.14. Act. 13.3.</note>. As with us <hi>Rogation</hi> and <hi>Ember weekes,</hi> and our Lent Faſts to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eepe in commemoration the memory of Chriſt, miraculous Faſt for us by ſuch an abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence as is proportioned to the ſize of nature not deſire, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.3. That as the Church hath her publique ſinnes, ſhee might appeare as one penitent before God in her Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and admit her excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40989:42"/>and ſcandalous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to a reconciliation upon their publique pennance, and ſatisfaction for open faults. Others there are arbitrary and elective for the time to our ſuperiours, and are either<note n="(a)" place="margin">Num. 6.3.4.</note> Apportionall or<note n="(b)" place="margin">Leuit. 16 29.31.</note> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grall, ever to boe obſerved (when called for Nationall, acted or enacted ſinnes) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule preſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.8. yet with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence from our Mother the Church, that if wee cannot all (though <hi>Qui poteſt capere, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piat,</hi>) wee may do what wee can to <hi>humble,</hi> not <hi>deſtroy</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, neither making our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies wantons nor drudges. And in this meaſure wee may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhape our private Faſts, by making them longer, or ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, totall, or apportionall, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:40989:42"/>occaſion, or our abilities re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. though the uſuall ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of the Sanctuary was a totall abſtinence from even till even<note n="(c)" place="margin">Lev. 16.29. &amp; 23.32. Joel. 1.2.</note>; But ſometimes practiſed with alteration. Thus <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 9, 9. <hi>Cornelius, Acts</hi> 10.30. <hi>Ezra,</hi> 10.6. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 4.16.2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.35. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Num.</hi> 6.3.4. not in an abſolute abſtinence, but hard dyet; only theſe cautions are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That for the time dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, we muſt obſerve it as a Sabboth day with equall ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe both for Piety and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It muſt be penall, for the afflicting our ſoules in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing food and other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, as an act of corrective, Juſtice and fruit of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40989:43"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.13. <hi>James</hi> 4.9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Pious in the exerciſe of our charitie, and other works of mercy, <hi>Eſay</hi> 58.6.10. <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.9.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laying aſide all outward ornaments,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ex. 33 6.</note> and caſting aſhes upon our heads (that is thoughts of our mortalities,) As the Rudder of the ſhip to ſteere us in an even and faſe courſe: for though naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be the Ladies pride, and beggers ſhame, let us be aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of nothing but our pride; but when beggers before God, not appeare brave toward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men, but uncloath our ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diveſt our ſoules of inwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vanities and appeare in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> moſt humble poſture before him, covering our ſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with ſackcloth out of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:40989:43"/>Poore mans wardrop; And winding our bodies in it as a Corps ready for buriall; by that ſilent act to ſpeake our ſelves fitter to lie in the ground then to breath upon it; mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every part a ſharer in our ſorrow as they were in our ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13. For thus tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our muſick into mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, our Organ with <hi>Iob,</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Job. 30.31.</note> into the voyce of weeping,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>37.</note> (our unaccented ſorrow expreſſed in our groanes and ſighes, and our <hi>chattering</hi> with <hi>the Crane,</hi> being the ſweeteſt melody in the eares of God) wee ſhall keepe our ſelves at home in thoughts of our owne vi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and by that confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enlarge our ſelves to run the round of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements; and by that circle here attaine a circle within a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40989:44"/>circle, infinite infolded hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in Heaven: So as our holy Faſts will prove the Vigils to the great Feſtivall of the ſupper of the Lamb where wee ſhall for ever feed upon joyes immenſe, unſpeakable, eternall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRayer</hi> is the very toppe branch of the worſhip of God, the breath and flame of faith, A duty in which wee acknowledge God in all his attributes and depend upon his providence, a divine grace inſpired, an arrow taken out of the Qiver of Heaven, which feathered with love, zeale, and perſeverance, ever pierces into Gods preſence above and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40989:44"/>conqers all difficulties below. It is like the Angel in <hi>Jacobs</hi> viſion that aſcends with our requeſts, and deſcends with Gods bleſſings; A nimble meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger or Mercury, that can travell in a thought, and fly upon the wings of the winde; for fill but its ſales with a gentle gale from a groane or ſigh<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ro. 8.26</note>, the holy ſpirit being its Pilot and Chriſt its pole-Star it will ſoone arrive at hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and returne with a rich lading of mercies. But then wee muſt be ſure as it proceeds from <hi>Faith,</hi> ſo it muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feighned; from <hi>zeale,</hi> it muſt be to Gods glory,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Jam. 5. Heb. 11.</note> from our <hi>hearts,</hi> they muſt bee pure,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pro. 15.8 Pſa. 50.16.17.66.18. Eccl. 8.11. Iſa 66.3.59.11. Pſal. 45.</note> for where the tongue is the ſpheare, the heart muſt be the center in all lifting up cleane hands without wrath
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40989:45"/>or doubting, and not onely cleane white with innocency, but active too in all things that may conduce to ſo high an end; for <hi>pro quo quis oret, pro eo laboret;</hi> hearts and hands, eyes and tongues, with all other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties ſhould concurre to the pulling downe of Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings upon our ſelves or the whole Church. <hi>Lam</hi> 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.47.123. Nay our very enemies who ought ever to be one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of our Prayers with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſpirituall mercies, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19, 18. <hi>I uke</hi> 6.23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. as well as our friends, nay more, as moſt wanting them.</p>
               <p>Now as Prayer is the genus (a comprehenſive word) ſo there are many ſpecies and ſeverall manners of Invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Orall, Mentall, Publike, Private, Extempore or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditate,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40989:45"/>and other Members and branches expreſſed by St. <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Tim. 1.3 Phil. 4.6, 7</note>, As ſupplication <hi>ex ſuppliciis,</hi> Prayers <hi>Ora rationis,</hi> Interceſſions for others, and giving of thankes for all, to make up a compleate body of Prayer which wee may againe ſumme up in Confeſſion of ſins, gratitude for Benefits, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for Mercies. But in the conſideration of theſe we ſhall not take them in any Method, but involvedly, as they twine and interweave one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and reduce all to <hi>private</hi> and <hi>publique</hi> Prayer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Private Prayer,</hi> where God gives the ſpirit of grace and ſupplication<note n="(l)" place="margin">Zach. 12.10. Gal. 4.6. Pſal. 25.4, 5.119.12.33.</note>, as the ſpring and fountaine from whence all mercies flow, is a duty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded as a meanes<note n="(m)" place="margin">Ph i. 4.6.</note>, and alwayes ſucceſſefull in regard
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40989:46"/>of the end of obtaining our deſires<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mat. 7.7 Jer. 33.3. Pro. 2.3.5. Ez. 36.37. Jer. 29. Deut. 4.7. Pſ. 86.5. Ro. 10.12. Jud. 20. Jam. 4.7. Lu. 11.13: Iſa. 65.24.</note>, If wee give God our whole heart<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pro. 23.26</note>, continue watchfull before Him with feare and fervency of ſpirit;<note n="(p)" place="margin">Col. 4.2. Ro. 12.11. Pſal. 2.11.5.7.</note> for the hearts of all the faithfull are compared to <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Vialls full of odors</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">Apoc. 3.8 Pſa. 141.2</note>, <hi>which is the Prayer of the Saints.</hi> And if zeale be the fire to make them aſcend and become a ſweete ſavour to God, our Prayer thus ſent up to Heaven under the great ſeale of love (like the Court Earwig) will never faile of a gratious audience and return. But when wee unclaſpe and anatomize our ſoules, and ſhame our ſelves in confeſſing our paſt rebellions before <hi>God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Joſh.</hi> 7.7. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 1. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8 <hi>Lev.</hi> 5. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.4. and by our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſement advance his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40989:46"/>He will forget what wee remember, and give not only more then we can deſire, but prevent us in asking<note n="(r)" place="margin">Iſa. 65: 24.</note>; for Prayer faithfully performed is Gods favorite and darling, and the iſſue of the ſoule, as children of the body, the one by a naturall, the other by a ſpirituall Generation; and of ſuch efficacy, though they want expreſſions to Midwife them forth, as they can in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other wayes deliver them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and never want a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all, though many times an orall voyce. For, as one obſerves upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. God hath his eare in our hearts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have any words in our mouths; nay<note n="(s)" place="margin">Ro. 8.26.</note> groans and ſighs do many times expreſſe the unexpreſſible ſecrets of them<note n="(t)" place="margin">Jo. 11.33.38.</note>. And the poſture of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40989:47"/>the eye ſpeakes the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoule, with good <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi>
                  <note n="(u)" place="margin">2 Chro. 20.12.</note>, Or it weepes a Prayer<note n="(w)" place="margin">Heb. 5.7 Lu. 7.44.47 Job. 16.20. Eccl. 35.15 Pſa. 6.8 38 39.42.72.79.</note> which is alwayes a ſtrong and prevayling, though ſilent, oratory with God; yet Hee is ſo graciouſly ready to conſider our wants and deſires, that though teares are the beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> glaſſe for him to behold u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in, Hee will ſometimes ſee a wet heart in a dry eye,<note n="(x)" place="margin">2 Chro. 20.12.</note> the waters in the veynes of the Earth before they bubble; accept our intentions, the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of a pious ſoule before they breake forth into any open ſtreames of ſorrow. And as the diſpoſition is thus often taken for the action, ſo actions alone are many times taken to be as expreſſive of inward affections and become opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Prayers. Thus <hi>Phineas</hi> is
<pb facs="tcp:40989:47"/>ſayd to pray, if wee compare <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.30.31. with <hi>Numb.</hi> 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 8. And acts of Juſtice are ſtyled Petitions, <hi>Jo.</hi> 8. <hi>Ion.</hi> 3. <hi>Pro.</hi> 21.3. As Prayers acts of Juſtice in becomming a ſacrifice to God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Publique Prayer</hi> is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and out rent of the ſoule we owe to God; And though it may take its denomination from a collection <hi>of two or three</hi> together, it is ever beſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the houſe of God, the place of Prayer,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat. 21.13. Lu. 19.45.46. 1 Kin. 8.2. Chro. 6.</note> And Gods reſidence<note n="(z)" place="margin">Hab. 2.20</note>, the chamber of preſence and Court of Requeſts, wherein he gives moſt gracious audience, and is for glory like the <hi>gate of Heaven</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 28.16, 17.</note> and a place ever accounted the joy of Saints and delight of God himſelfe, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.30. &amp; 26.2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.7.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40989:48"/>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.4. &amp; 48 &amp; 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; 84, &amp; 122, &amp; 128, &amp; 26, &amp; 116.114. &amp; 132.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14.16.4.17. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.17. So as there princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally even with <hi>David</hi> in the <hi>great Congregation</hi> we ought to muſter up our devotions, though chiefly thoſe Prayen the Church wee live in hath leavied or aſſeſſed for God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſervice, as a publique teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our piety for the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning others by our example, inflaming of zeale, ſending up a better perfume (as many flowers in one Noſegay), and the giving them a greater prevalency; for <hi>unita vis for tior.</hi> If there be a promiſe to a few, much more to many cloſe knit together in the <hi>unity of the ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>the bond of peace</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Eph. 4.3.</note> the outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40989:48"/>in worſhip, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. Society being like a faggot on fire, wherein one ſticke keeps another glowing; or as ſtones in an arch, every one holding and faſtning his fellow: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſolitude wants many ſuch advantages; which was the reaſon that God playing his own Criticke could make no exception to his owne work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, but found all <hi>very good</hi> but mans being alone. And therefore let us not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from nor in Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique worſhip, which He ſo much hates as He would not commend his ſecond daies worke (as one obſerves upon <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 1.7.) becauſe it was a worke of diviſion. Though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here is a latitude in <hi>private prayer,</hi> ſo as the groanes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Spirit are ſometimes the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40989:49"/>beſt eloquence, the Orator of tranſient and unfixt ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations being often heard b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, when not taken noti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of by our ſelves,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſa. 32.6</note> and purpoſe accepted for performances <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> In publique places all ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be done to the edification a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> building up one another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our moſt holy faith, for whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the underſtanding as well as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections muſt meet in the cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> notion of things we pray fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> And therefore though exten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> porary prayer be lawfull, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> formes for publique uſe I co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be the beſt, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> commendable, and not on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> allowed in all ages, practi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> by all Churches ſince the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times (except for ſome latter yeeres) but command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by God himſelfe<note n="(e)" place="margin">Deut. 26.3, 5.20.3. Num. 6.23 Exod. 15.1 21. Iſa. 38 20. Matth. 6.</note>. For it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not the words, the waxe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:40989:49"/>receives the impreſſion, but the Spirit the ſtampe that gives it, that makes our evidence pleadable in the court of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And therefore let us conſider</p>
               <p n="1">Firſt, the infinite diſtance between God and us, which ſhould make all our addreſſes to be full of awfull reverence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o him, and not offer a perfun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, raw, and indigeſted prayer, <hi>the Sacrifice of fooles,</hi> to the God of all wiſdome. And this made <hi>Salomon</hi> ſay, <hi>Be not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with thy mouth, and let not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hy heart be haſty to utter any thing before God; for God is in Heaven, and thou upon Earth; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>herefore let thy words be few</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.2.</note>. And if the diſtance betwixt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee and an earthly Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ught to create ſuch appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40989:50"/>as the Prophet <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi</hi> ſpeaks of, Chap. 1.8. ſhould we not be choiſe in our offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories to God, whoſe vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafing of our beſt is a conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention, there being no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion or commenſuration i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what we owe, and what w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can doe? Onely as in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things, ſo in manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Spirituall Sacrifices, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our offerings be of the firſt and chiefeſt of the flocke<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mal. 1.11</note>; ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> higheſt outward abilities and inward graces concurring;<note place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>nunquam in odoribus Sacriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ciorum delectatus eſt Domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſi in fide &amp; deſiderio off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, when God giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Spirit of prayer, and othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Divine gifts and graces, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are not to make us perfect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:40989:50"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> inſtant, nor to aſſiſt us by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aies immediate and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, as in the firſt planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſtianity; but by mediate and milde courſes; He carries us from one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame to another, from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>elity to true believing, by preaching<note n="(h)" place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> : not that it workes phyſically, but as an inſtrument, as the window <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onveyes and lets in light; Nor doth he give the gift of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reaching</hi> without ſtudy, nor of <hi>prayer</hi> without premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; in both comparing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things with Spirituall things<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.13.</note>, and from thence forming their productions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d improving their abilities. For as one obſerves upon 1 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or.</hi> 16. that is firſt that is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and then that which is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40989:51"/>Spirituall, all infuſed habit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> working themſelves up to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeverall degrees of perfection in men (though all imperfect in this life) by way of improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and acquiſition, and make uſe of nature to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, not deſtroy it, to act by it, and not with the bond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> woman to throw it out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doores, out of Gods ſervice<note n="k" place="margin">Jud. v. 10</note> For the Spirit doth but <hi>help our infirmities,</hi> not exclud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them<note n="(l)" place="margin">Rom. 8 26</note>. And therefore h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that will neglect meanes to depend or preſume of mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied Miracles, may fancy himſelfe into damnation, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> buſes himſelfe, not God, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> commands us <hi>to ſpeake as hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Oracles</hi>
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.11.</note>, not lightly, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deliberately, taking ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forme from thence, or inno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:40989:51"/>bling the faculties of nature by ſtudy, and the aſſiſtances of me Spirit, to frame ſomething in analogy to them. Thus we may be ſaid to <hi>pray with the Spirit, and with the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alſo</hi>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">1 Cor. 14 15.</note>.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Set-formes of prayer are warranted to us by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the beſt men and times, may of Chriſt himſelfe<note n="(o)" place="margin">Mat. 26.37, 44. Mar. 14.35 39. Luk. 22.41 42.</note>, and the holy Angels in Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, where no imperfection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">Rev. 5.9, 12. &amp; 7.12.</note>; with the authority of a full Jury of men inſpired, whoſe practice gave a verdict for it. Thus <hi>Moſes</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">Num. 6.23. Exod. 15.1 21. 2 Chro. 5.13.26, &amp; 6.41, 42 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 38.9, 10 Pal. 136. Deut. 20.3. &amp; 26.3, 5. 1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 26. Rev. 15.3.</note>, with many (nay all) others, in that ſet formes of bleſſing and prayſing God was uſed by the whole Church: nay ſung and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40989:52"/>ſaid in Heaven; for ſo we ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> finde that of <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed out of <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 14.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.6, 7.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Formes of prayer a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> commanded, and a pattern given not onely to direct an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> regulate our prayers by, as is in <hi>Matthew, After this mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pray</hi>
                  <note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat. 6.9.</note>, but enjoyned <hi>in ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> materiae &amp; forma verborum,</hi> the words themſelves; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> St. <hi>Luke</hi>
                  <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Luk. 11.2.</note> 
                  <hi>When you pray, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Our Father;</hi> that is, ſay the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very words. And this mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> St. <hi>John</hi> (as Divines concen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from <hi>Luke</hi> 11.1.) teach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Diſciples a forme for <hi>publiq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and conſtant uſe both for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, edification, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of many other abuſe and inconveniences. For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſpirit of prayer lieth not in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:40989:52"/>length nor ſtrength of words, but in the devotion of the heart; and that I am ſure muſt needs be moſt vigorous when there is nothing to diſturbe it. By which reaſon the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding having before dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the matter, and ſetled it ſelfe, may better goe along with the affections in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated or <hi>ſet forme,</hi> then it can in an extemporary prayer of anothers making. Becauſe we muſt firſt throughly and conſcientiouſly weigh his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions before we can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>center our devotions in <hi>Amen,</hi> which is a ſhort recapitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, and the duty of every Chriſtian<note n="(t)" place="margin">1 Chro. 16.36. Deut. 27.15. 1 Cor. 14.16.</note>. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this advantage they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſefull for the helpe of the ignorant, the preſervation of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40989:53"/>the unity of faith and charity and to hedge and fence in the true Church from all fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call extravagant mixtures, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> froth or crudity of ſome men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> braines; and ſometimes dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricall oppoſitions of the Miniſters prayers in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Congregations, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their engagement of opinions or affections, which may diſturbe and diſtract the beſt ſetled devotion<note n="(v)" place="margin">Exod. 30 35. Deut. 26.5 Pſal. 96. 1 Cor. 14.40. Ecd. 5.2.</note>, even turning our prayers into ſinne, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.7. Nor is this a limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit more then an ordinary, voluntary, varied prayer, of a private man in publique devotions, but a maintaining of our liberty; for we may pray with the Spirit in both; ſince it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Spirits praying,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40989:53"/>the act of the inward man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with the expreſſions of another. For if it were otherwiſe, then thoſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to pray by the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary tranſmiſſion of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> would not one croſſe and contradict another in their petitions, in that it is a Spirit of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> not of <hi>diviſion;</hi> but muſt be able at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſt to ſhew us ſome convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing evidence to declare which of them have the true Spirit, by ſome extraordinary gifts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe of <hi>ſpeaking divers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ongues,</hi> or <hi>propheſying</hi> ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore without the uſe of ſtudy of Arts; whereas in the native and proper ſence of praying with the Spirit all may agree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wee conſider it in its firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctuall motions, or its teaching
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40989:54"/>us the matter and manner o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our prayers, as well as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dictating the words. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the power of prayer conſiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> chiefly in the extenſion of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit, not in the language o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the tongue; the intenſneſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our zeale, not the fulneſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our expreſſions; though in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we ought to contrive them in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the moſt contracted and path<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tick way we can, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quicker the Bow is drawn, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſharper it ſhoots, when ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding bent to the height ſlac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> its force. Which made ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Saviour Chriſt chooſe his ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> forme, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.37, 44. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> often repeated out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and other holy men premed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tate what they were to offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 9.14. Otherwaies <hi>Dav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> would not have ſaid, <hi>Pond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:40989:54"/>my words, O Lord,</hi> had hee not firſt weighed them him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Now if it be granted that it formes may be lawfull (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat knowing man will deny it?) but that premeditation of the matter, not words, is more uſefull; I deny it upon the former grounds: And with the Apoſtles adviſe ſhall not in this truſt to any private ſpirit, or at leaſt not preferre it to that more publique one of the Church in her Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, Nationall, and generall Councels; ſhe being both firſt and moſt concerned in the promiſes of Divine aſſiſtance, who hath ever compoſed ſhort and powerfull prayers moſt ponducing to Gods glory, and the ſtirring up of the affections
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40989:55"/>for publique uſe, with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſervation of a power to va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them as occaſion ſhould invit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſtill <hi>making the ſpirits of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Prophets ſubject to the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note n="(w)" place="margin">1 Cor. 14 32.</note> in this and all things elſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that concerne the due orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the publique Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, that the quit-rent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we pay into Gods Exchequer in acknowledgement of our fealties and ſubjection may not be in coyne embaſed but currant, and bearing the ſtamp of authority. Thus in the Law where the Prieſt was to offer for the ſinnes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, his Sacrifice was preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, though they as ſingle perſons were to meaſure their offering to their abilities; but then in proportion though it were meane and poore, it was
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40989:55"/>to be pure, and of the beſt they could bring for Sacrifice to Gods Altar. Nor is this a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eater reſtraining of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſpirit then a preſcribing the matter, and heads upon which he is to frame his peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, making him onely the Dictionary to ſit them with words; unleſſe you conceive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is the muſicke of the eare as well as that of the heart God delights in; whereas indeed the fruits and effects of the Spirit are Eſſentials, not Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonials; the body of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not the dreſſe and cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. And therefore I could wiſh in all things of publique worſhip ſome Sinewes and Nerves to hold all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt in a firme union, ſome ſymbols of publique
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40989:56"/>communion, that all irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, impertinences and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties might be baniſhed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſolemne and publique me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and our Church lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jeruſalem all one in it ſelfe</hi>
                  <note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſa. 122.3</note> The whole Congregation <hi>one man,</hi> ſerving God wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reverence and feare, truth the inward man, and an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble decency without. For <hi>God ſtand in the Congregatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> it will ſure be fit for us,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> To come.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> To bow down.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> To kneele before the Lord maker<note n="(y)" place="margin">Pal. 95.</note>.</item>
                  </list> and uſe all other expreſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that may declare and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devotion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 134.3, 87, 30, 132, 7. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.41, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Ezra</hi> 8 5, 9, 5. <hi>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 6, 5. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.4. But for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:40989:56"/>referre to what I have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſſed upon the title of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion.</p>
               <p>And upon theſe grounds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Church hath ever thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mes of prayer moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll and neceſſary for Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſe of prayer; where there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould be a daily Sacrifice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ffered<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 13.</note>, (even the calves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our lips<note n="(b)" place="margin">Oſe. 14.2</note>, though not of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur ſtall) which hath been of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>te ſo much neglected, as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>onceive, by reaſon of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſuſe, and the ſuſpenſion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſe injunctions that have in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rmer times obliged to it, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I cannot but wiſh (if our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ommon Prayer booke may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot be againe reſtored, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urged from thoſe ſuppoſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rrors ſome tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nces have been offended at)
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40989:57"/>that yet all formes may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be aboliſhed; ſince it may eaſily ſhewed that the Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> neither under the Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Goſpell, if in a ſetled and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous condition) ever want a ſet Liturgy for the regu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her publique devo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and that the want of amongſt us hath at leaſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcured (if not extinguiſhed much of that Piety for wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this Nation was ſo bleſſed, it became the envy of all thers; and I hope God of great and abundant mercy w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> put it into the hearts and reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of thoſe that have juſt power and calling for to cauſe the <hi>Beſaleels</hi> of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> times (thoſe men that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath endued with moſt w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> dome and cunning for the bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40989:57"/>of his Church) to hew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d prepare ſome ſtones, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ake them fit for his <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at every unskilfull workman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay not bring his rough and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ncaſt thoughts, and be ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ering and ſeeking for matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen they ſhould with it knit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> into the building; but have ready moulded and ſquared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y the moſt ancient and beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tternes even of the pureſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Primitive times; as ours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as formerly modeld, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> uſe and ornament (like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e poliſhed corners of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>emple) wherein it was their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>udence as well as Piety to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mpoſe their ſolemne Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce of ſuch parts as might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt advance Religion, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me the affections, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y with the Ages infirmities,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40989:58"/>and conditions of men; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> reading ſome parts of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Scriptures, with interpoſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Prayers, Pſalmes, Hymne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Spirituall Songs; that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thoughts might be thereby th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> more elevated, and Gods pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes manifeſted.</p>
               <p>Praiſes for benefits, Praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for preſent and future want with an interweaving tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> duties, that the returnes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit might be the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe and fervent; The inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour powers of the ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (which cannot long contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> without paine in any one p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture) kept up; and the u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding (the higher pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the minde) be raiſed wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the contemplation of tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Divine and revealed myſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> by this variety to becom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:40989:58"/>helpes and ſpurres to one an other, and take new inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ons to pray from hearing the Word read.</p>
               <p>From all which conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions the Church hath accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly compoſed her Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and contracted the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of her publique Formes into feweſt words, knowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is the vertuouſneſſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind, not the copiouſneſſe of the Language; fervent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>titions not teadious tautol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gies; much praying in few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ords, not vaine babling in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng prayers, that is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to God; ever ſupplying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir defects by the repetition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lords Prayer in every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>verall returne to that duty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>owing that God is not nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ated with one and the ſame
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40989:59"/>diſh (as we in our diets) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Spirit hand it into his preſence; nor are we forbid to pray the ſame Prayer often over, if we repeate it not as a charme, or place power in the words (like the vagabond Jewes Exorſiſts in <hi>Acts</hi> the 19, 13, 16.) As if they had any Phyſicall or innate vertue i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them, or did produce any thing from being pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; But if wee give form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to that matter by the Spirit moving it, we pray well i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Name of Jeſus<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Io. 2.</note> though beſt when we uſe his words or ſhape our Prayers by tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abſolute Copy hee hath le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> us; and then they will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhort, leaſt by it we ſeem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſet too little a value upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> waighty a duty; nor too lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:40989:59"/>for publique uſe, leaſt the weakneſſe and imbecillities of ſome in mixed Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould ſtay behind or ſtop in the way, and not be able to goe along in the duty; But ſo tempered as may keep up all mens devotions to the higheſt pitch they can be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; for too much laſſitude of ſpirits diſpoſeth to ſleepe and laſie poſtures; whereas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> percing brevity holds the intentions of the mind moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rect and leaſt ſubject to flag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging (like an Arrow, as I ſaid that ſtaies but little at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent before it be ſhot) nay wee ſoare to Heaven ſooner upon the wings of ardent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, then the traine of long diſcourſes<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eccl. 5.</note>, which like a Thread never ſo well
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40989:60"/>ſpunne weakens and ravel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when drawne beyond it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> length; onely let us be ſure to give them theſe Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That they be made in Faith<note n="(e)" place="margin">Heb. 11. Jam. 1.</note>; for as Prayer is the mouth of Faith, ſo Faith is the heart of Prayer.</p>
               <p>Secondly, with zeale: for it is the fervent prayer of the Righteous that prevaileth much<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 38.55. Jam. 5.</note>; and the flame that aſcends when the dull and heavy matter dies in its aſhes and proves its owne grave.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, with vorifera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as well as intention; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and vocall<note n="(g)" place="margin">Hoſ. 14.2.1, 3.</note> as well as mentall; Thus <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 141.142.1. <hi>For he cried,</hi> ſaith the Text (to ſhewhis inward
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40989:60"/>fire and fervency) with his voyce to give it the ornament and advantage hee could; knowing that as the Spouſe muſt be all glorious within, ſo her Dreſſe ſhould be of Needleworke and wrought Gold; and therefore let us not onely praiſe him upon the well tuned Cymbal (the heart,) but upon the loude Cymbal (the tongue,) to ſhew forth his honour, and ſpeake his praiſes in both.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, with importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which made <hi>David</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double his voyce, and eccho backe his owne words; For this is the Spirituall Engine by which Heaven ſuffers vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and the violent take it by force; ſo as he that askes ſhall obtaine, or if not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40989:61"/>by asking, will finde by ſeeking; or if not finde by ſeeking, will be ſure by kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king (a perſevering importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) to force Heaven gates<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for with <hi>Abraham</hi> as long as we ceaſe not praying God will not ceaſe giving.</p>
               <p>Fifthly and laſtly, with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility: for like well layden Trees the more we are hung with Gods graces, the lower they bend us; and not onely invite Gods eye to behold (but himſelfe to reſide in) us, who hath no Heaven upon Earth but the humble ſoule to inhabit<note n="(h)" place="margin">Iſ. 57.15.</note>; and who would not doe any thing to purchaſe ſuch a gueſt? debaſe himſelfe to be ſo exalted, and with the no leſſe good then great Patriarke, Preface his
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40989:61"/>Prayer with a humble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion of his owne vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in ſaying I am but duſt and aſhes, nothing either in foundation or ſtructure but the moſt baſe, barren, and uſeleſſe Earth? neither is this grace a ſingle vertue, but as it were the Arke that keepes all other holy things in it.</p>
               <p>Now if we thus ſucke the breſts of his promiſes, and have an eye of faith alwaies upon him, his will againe meets ours; and then as the neutraliſts obſerve, (when the nurſe centers in the childs at the tet, and keepes in that conjunction) the Milke will flow and nouriſh us both in body and ſoule to eternall life; for the body is the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Holy Ghoſt here,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40989:62"/>and hath Heaven provided for it hereafter: if it beard its part in the Duty, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hopes for a ſhare in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>Now having thus farre con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the duty of prayer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the manner of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it, we ſhould doe well to allow it ſome ſet times; or if none, make it but one continuall duty; for ſo the Apoſtle commands us, 1 <hi>Theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 5.17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pray alwaies</hi> in habit, if not is art. <hi>Ph.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.2. Thought in act too as often as our owne private retirements or other opportunities invite us, which was the reaſon the Church ever had her <hi>houres of prayer</hi> conſecrated and appointed for her publique devotions, <hi>Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:40989:62"/>5.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 119.164. <hi>Marke</hi> 1.5, 40. <hi>Job</hi> 38.7. <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.19. is in the morning, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 92.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The third houre of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.15. <hi>Mar.</hi> 15.25. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10. The ſixth houre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the day, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.9. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 55.18. The ninth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oure of the day, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.55. And at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24 63. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 65.8. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.33, 35. But if we cannot this, let us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe what we may; and if not <hi>even times a day,</hi> with <hi>David,</hi> it us at leaſt <hi>Morning, Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> and at <hi>Noone,</hi> praiſe our God<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.164. Pſa. 55.17.</note>, making it the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey to open our paſſage to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l ſecular imployments, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhut them out when we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ire to reſt; for then our Prayers like an Heavenly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halation
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40989:63"/>drawn forth by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit of God will as re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>freſhing dewes fall down<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againe upon our labour, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make them pleaſing and fruit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p>But it may be objected tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods deareſt ſervants, thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> frequent were not alwaie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſucceſſefull in this duty, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſometimes have prayed them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves into a wearineſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ection, and ſilence, if n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> deſpaire almoſt of being hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 77.69.3.119.8.8.123 <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. <hi>Job</hi> 30.20. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 22, 23, 26.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, that God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſpleaſure is ſometimes h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> favour to us. And that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not giving ſometimes he gives us his greateſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſings; and doth not heare u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:40989:63"/>either becauſe he would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and make us more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, or to try our pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, exerciſe our faith and obedience, encreaſe our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and make us the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore value his benefits when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> have obtained them<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 15.28. 2 Cor. 12.7, 8. Cant. 3.1, 4. Luke 22.44. Pſa. 37.40 1 Pet. 4.</note>. though he is alwaies giving ſomething equivalent (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od) if not the thing we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke even when wee aske it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough perhaps not diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to us; Thus to<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 12 8, 9.</note> St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and to our Saviour, who was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t heard in that the Cup did not paſſe from him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. and yet was heard in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od gave him other comforts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> poyſe it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7. So that is ſubmiſſion to his Fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll obtained the ſatisfaction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f his owne; whereas ſome
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40989:64"/>in being heard are not hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 106 15. &amp; 69.22. Mal. 2.9.</note>, in that God then curſe his own bleſſings, and with the fruit ſends a worme t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſume it, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.31. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.7 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.30, 31.</p>
               <p>But to wind up all, if w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> moderate our requeſts and bound them with ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and remaine as fixt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the beliefe of Gods ſpecial providence to us in all va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of fortune, as we d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the beliefe of a God<note n="(d)" place="margin">Matth. 6.33, 34. Prov. 30. Jam. 1. 1 Kings 3.</note> and then aske <hi>(in ordine)</hi> firſt the dew of Heaven, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the fatneſſe of the Earth which a ſhaming confeſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our owne vileneſſe<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pro. 28.9, 13. Pſal. 31.51</note>, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>) ſo ſome obſerve prayer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe is in the originall to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> derived from thence) we ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> obtaine all we can deſire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:40989:64"/>by a kinde of omnipotency <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here is in a faithfull and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayer<note n="(f)" place="margin">Matth. 11 12. 10.14.13.14. Jam 1.4, 5. 1 Jo. 5.14, 15. Exo. 32.10.</note>, raiſe our ſalves above the World and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll in it; for the carnall Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is but of the Earth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orthly; Philoſophy bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, as it were, carries a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orall good man ſomething <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ther, but then it leaves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>im in the middle Orbes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke a meteor hanging in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re above earth, not ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>igh as Heaven; higher then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſenſuall, but below the Sprituall man. And the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> praying Chriſtian onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>bes Heaven and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion it under a vaile of fleſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ving all things elſe under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for hee can interrupt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> motions of Heavenly bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, as in <hi>Hezekias;</hi> maſter
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:40989:65"/>the Elements<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 43.</note>, open th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bowels of the Earth, <hi>Num<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 16. Plucke up the ſluces <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Clouds, and pave th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> waters; nay by a Religion impudence and holy violend can give a Law, as it we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the Law-giver<note n="(h)" place="margin">Exod. 32. Deut. 9.14 20.</note>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> verſing his decrees, <hi>Judge</hi> 10.13, 15. Conquering Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 14.9, 12. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifing the Graves, and bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their dead to life, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the children were in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> birth, but wanted ſtrength to bring forth, <hi>Jo.</hi> 11.22, 38. And refuſing all refuſal, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 32.25, 28. breake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> through the repulſe of God himſelfe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.26, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> But in all wee muſt ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Gods Word the ground a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> matter of our prayers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:40989:65"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.25. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. His will he Rule, <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.14. The holy Spirit the life and principle, <hi>Tom.</hi> 8.36. <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Job</hi> 37.19. preparing, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.27. ſtirring up, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.7, 8. and fixing our hearts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon God alone, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 57.7, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and ſummoning all our powers, like ſo many Lines to meet in Him as their Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 103. And then the man thus Sainted here may become a <hi>Moſes</hi> to appeaſe Gods wrath againſt a Nation, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Phineas</hi> to ſtand betweene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e living and the dead, to true away, and quench the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mes of a devouring plague. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Elijah,</hi> Chariots and Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n, a Banke to ſtop the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ndation of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, even the ſtrength of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:40989:66"/>
                  <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and not onely Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes againſt an Enemy, but a roofe and covering too a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt judgements from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And having thus fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed my weake and ſhort meditations, I wiſh the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle gayle of Gods holy Spirit that fils the ſayles (as prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of all Spirituall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) may waft you into the harbour of ſure peace an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> acquieſcence in him; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that theſe ſparkes and glint merings of conſolation a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> direction blowne abroad from that fire hee hath kindled a my heart may enflame you all that read this rough and unpoliſhed piece with the ſame affections I commend is to you, not looking at the inſtrument, but hand that
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:40989:66"/>workes by it; for if you reape advantage, and gather fruit from this barren Tree of my planting, the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the meanes will be in improvement of GODS glory. Onely I ſhall deſire you will forget the Authour, and looke upon the Object, or accept the odour of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility I ſend with it, as my oblation to expiate for my other faylings; which cannot but make him little in your eyes that is nothing in his owne; The Earthen Pipe onely which God hath uſed to convey ſome drops (I hope) if not ſtreames of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing comforts to your ſoules. And however <hi>looking to Jeſus the Author and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ator of my faith</hi> and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe<note n="(i)" place="margin">Heb. 12.2</note>,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:40989:67"/>I am reſolved with patience to <hi>endure the croſſe,</hi> and <hi>deſpiſe the ſhame</hi> that can be caſt upon me for my honeſt intentions; being confident God will accept my well aimed though ill ſhot Arrow, firſt taken out of his Quiver, and now brought to His Altar; where I deſire to offer up my ſelfe with it to be both Prieſt and Sacrifice, though all be leſſe then the leaſt of his mercies which are my guide and ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>port here, and will be my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hereafter: when he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall tranſport me from Earth to Heaven, from a valley of teares to a mount of joyes; and thoſe not fading or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying (like the ripeſt and fulleſt blown pleaſures here;)
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:40989:67"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to fulneſſe of joyes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either waine or eclipſe; and that fulneſſe not narrow, or bounded, but in ſuch a full meaſure, or meaſure of fulneſſe, as knowes no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or degrees; and that not momentary, but for ever and ever; in a continuall multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication and ſucceſſion of happineſſe; which will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſatisfie, never ſatiate, in that God is the object, the joy immenſe; and all no leſſe eternall then God himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40989:68"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40989:68"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
